<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of god [et] man but with out</title>
            <title>Life of Saint Margaret.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104383</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840121</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840121</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 137:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of god [et] man but with out</title>
                  <title>Life of Saint Margaret.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Mychell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: The life of Saint Margaret.</note>
                  <note>Title from first line of text, leaf b3r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Margaret, --  of Antioch, Saint --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Margaret, --  of Antioch, Saint --  Legends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragmentary_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4593:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4593:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <l>Of god &amp; man but with out p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itence</l>
               <l>And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion with fylth and v<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Of dedely ſynnys preſumyth to accede</l>
               <l>Vn to the holy myſteriſe in dede</l>
               <l>He etith &amp; drynkith his dome to hym for ſothe</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>che dedely ſynner that curſidly ſo dothe</l>
               <l>But we therfore that many day before</l>
               <l>with confeſſion of oure ſynnes ſoore</l>
               <l>with penitence are chaſtyſid &amp; made thynne</l>
               <l>with leane lent and faſt ageyn oure ſynne</l>
               <l>with almeſſe doyng &amp; bitter teris wepyng</l>
               <l>And fro ſynnes ſluggye &amp; fro ſlepyng</l>
               <l>Are cleney waſſhe with outyn foul enfection</l>
               <l>Than in the day of holy reſurrection</l>
               <l>Of oure lorde we to his borde accede</l>
               <l>In feyth catholique with fleſſh &amp; blode vs fede</l>
               <l>Of the vnſpottyd lambe of criſt ieſu</l>
               <l>Not vn to dome but to encreſe of vertu</l>
               <l>we it teceyue to remiſſion of ſynne</l>
               <l>Finally the bliſſe of heuyn to wynne</l>
               <l>That is callid helthfull beatitude</l>
               <l>It for to take with the hoole multitude</l>
               <l>Of ioy &amp; bliſſe to alle oure reparation</l>
               <l>we take this feſt as to oure preparation</l>
               <l>And thus my frendes it nedith you to do</l>
               <l>Theſe textis and reſons for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vn to</l>
               <l>whan this peple in general had ꝑceyuid</l>
               <l>The qwenys wordꝭ &amp; ſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyuid</l>
               <l>Theſe textis holy &amp; trew expoſition</l>
               <l>Her wyſe wordꝭ of trew humble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition</l>
               <l>They coude anſwere in no maner wyſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4593:2"/>
For ripe ſentence with wordis ware &amp; wiſe</l>
               <l>But when they knew the chirchis inſtitution<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thens forwarde to thexecutions</l>
               <l>Of holy chirchis rite &amp; gouernaunce</l>
               <l>They toke to them this gentil obſeruaunce</l>
               <l>In parceyuing of this helthful myſtery</l>
               <l>And kept it forth with conſcience good &amp; mery</l>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Preterea in aliquibus locis. <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ANd in ſcotland alſo in dyuers placꝭ</l>
                     <l>Men ther were I trowe for lakke of gracꝭ</l>
                     <l>Ageyn holy chirchis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetude</l>
                     <l>That vſid to ſey myſſ that peple rude</l>
                     <l>with out the chirchis powere &amp; licence</l>
                     <l>Abhoiable was this inſolence</l>
                     <l>The which myſſe vſe this bleſſid holy qwene</l>
                     <l>In that erroure in no wyſe wolde ſuſtene</l>
                     <l>In goddis cauſe ſhe ſette her hert on fire</l>
                     <l>with al her ſtudy it was her hole deſire</l>
                     <l>For to deſtroye &amp; bryng to nowght y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rite</l>
                     <l>That after ward none durſt in ſoyl no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſite</l>
                     <l>So preſume or of that fecte appere</l>
                     <l>In alle the londe of ſcottꝭ ferr ne new</l>
                     <l>Alſo they vſid ayens the reuerence</l>
                     <l>Of holy ſonday ageyn criſtys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>placence</l>
                     <l>In ſeruile werkꝭ to be laborious</l>
                     <l>But the qwene deuout &amp; vertuous</l>
                     <l>She wyd theyr defaut by autorite</l>
                     <l>And by reſon to ech in his degre</l>
                     <l>Seyeng thus that criſtꝭ holy day</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4593:2"/>
which is ſonday was ordeynyd this is no nay</l>
                     <l>For criſtꝭ high bleſſid reſurrection</l>
                     <l>That euery criſten man ſhuld haue affection</l>
                     <l>It to haue in laude &amp; veneration</l>
                     <l>That we ſhuld do noo werk nor operation</l>
                     <l>That were ſeruile for fro ſeruilite</l>
                     <l>Of the fende his bondage &amp; pooſte</l>
                     <l>we were bought as wel we knowyn alle</l>
                     <l>Thus are we fre after that we were thralle</l>
                     <l>That day we ſhuld be deuout &amp; holy</l>
                     <l>Kepyng vs fro nycete ſynne &amp; foly</l>
                     <l>This affermyth the pope ſeynt gregory</l>
                     <l>wher he ſeyth thus in his deuout ſtory</l>
                     <l>In the ſonday no man put hym in preaſe</l>
                     <l>Fro ſeruile werkꝭ but fro that labowr ceaſe</l>
                     <l>Inſiſt to prayer in al maner wiſe</l>
                     <l>In goſtly labour ſhuld he ſo deuiſe</l>
                     <l>That if owght of vice and inſolence</l>
                     <l>By ſix dayes before of necligence</l>
                     <l>In the hole weke it happynyd to be done</l>
                     <l>That in ſonday that cometh after ſone</l>
                     <l>Of criſtis riſyng ſhuld be expiation</l>
                     <l>Clene by praierꝭ in goſtly conſolation</l>
                     <l>And ſeynt Gregor the pope &amp; holy clerk</l>
                     <l>A certeyn man for an erthly werk</l>
                     <l>Done on ſonday eſpied in probation</l>
                     <l>He ſmote with curſyng &amp; ſtrait increpation</l>
                     <l>with hert blamyng &amp; them that hym alſo</l>
                     <l>So conſeylid &amp; ſtyrid hym ther to</l>
                     <l>He Iugid them for to be denouncid</l>
                     <l>By .ii. moneth is curſid it was ꝓnouncid</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4593:3"/>
In opyn chirch this was his decre</l>
                     <l>Til it was correcte it wold no other be</l>
                     <l>whan the reſons of the qwene deuout</l>
                     <l>wel autoriſid were thus brought about</l>
                     <l>They were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludid &amp; cowd not ageyn ſay</l>
                     <l>But that they muſt kepe holy the ſonday</l>
                     <l>Fro werk ſeruile &amp; ſo they did in deede</l>
                     <l>Fro thens forward the better for to ſpede</l>
                     <l>And forther more vnleful mariagꝭ</l>
                     <l>Of ſtepmodres had yey in vſagꝭ</l>
                     <l>And that a man ſhulde wedde his brotheris wife</l>
                     <l>Aftir that he was paſſid fro this life</l>
                     <l>Theſe were vſed &amp; therfor the qwene</l>
                     <l>Theſe curſid vſes ſhe coude not ſuſtene</l>
                     <l>And ſeyd that all feythful peple muſt</l>
                     <l>Her curſid vſe for ſakyn &amp; her luſt</l>
                     <l>And as dethe ſuch mariage eſcheu</l>
                     <l>And to good vſe conforme them in vertue</l>
                     <l>And in that lond were many thingꝭ mo</l>
                     <l>Of wikkid rite &amp; curſid vſe alſo</l>
                     <l>Ageyn the chirchis goodely ordynance</l>
                     <l>which in that counſel by her gouernance</l>
                     <l>were adnullyd da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>puyd &amp; caſſate</l>
                     <l>And fro thoo bowndes fully extirpate</l>
                     <l>Out of the realme by her prouidence</l>
                     <l>Such was her witte prudence &amp; ſapiens</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <trailer>
                  <l>Explicit ſcða diſtinctio &amp; incipit tertia</l>
                  <l>Cum enim de ſalute. <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>.</l>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>ALſo more ouer when ſhe of ſoules helth</l>
                  <l>And wiſedome ſpake &amp; of goſtly welth</l>
               </lg>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4593:3"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
